You will also agree with me that today if you go to buy
an average scooter or bike, it
costs at least ₹1 lakh and this is
just the beginning.  After this, there is petrol,
service, maintenance, accessories, the expenses
never end and it is the era of inflation.  Most
two wheelers are now taken on loan.  Now
this creates problems for showrooms, dealers and bike manufacturing
companies.  But
who bears all this risk?  Who is at risk?
Yours.  Just imagine, if this bike gets stolen
or a major accident happens
, then neither the bank EMI will stop
nor will we have
this bike to use.
To cover this risk, it is very important for us to have a two
wheeler insurance policy.
But the question is, do you know
what damages are covered in your bike insurance policy?  What is a
first party and third party bike
insurance policy?
Which coverage and which
insurance policy should we take for a new bike or an expensive bike?
Which policy would be right for an old bike which runs less?
This one video will
make you almost an expert on bike insurance so that next time you
go to the agent to renew your policy,
you will know most of the things.  And after all, it is
not just about money, it is also about peace.  It
is also important to have peace of mind.  So
let us know what are
those secrets of the best bike insurance policy, those
secrets which no one has told you.  If
any bike or two wheeler meets with an accident,
then there can be two types of damage.
Suppose I am riding a bike, then firstly
my own bike can get damaged
and secondly my bike can cause damage to some other person or
some vehicle.
I can cover both these damages in my bike insurance
policy.  But for this
I should have the right bike insurance policy
which provides both these coverages.  There are
two types of bike
insurance or two wheeler insurance
policies based on the coverage.  The first is third party
insurance policy.  Under this, the
claim is made only for the loss suffered by the other person.
I cannot file a claim for my bike
and it is necessary to have at
least this third party insurance policy to legally drive on Indian roads.  The
second type is the first party
comprehensive policy.  Both
losses are covered under this.  That means
I can also claim for whatever happened to my bike.
And if the other person
files a third party claim against me, then that
liability will also be of my insurance company.
Because both are covered under this first party policy.
That is why it is
also called comprehensive insurance or first party insurance.  Now
which of these two bike insurance
policies should you take.  I will also tell you this
later in this video.  But let us
first know what insurance we get or have to take with the new bike.
Before 2019, when buying a new bike,
you only had to take a one-year comprehensive
insurance policy.  That is, in which
both these losses would be covered.
But many people did not renew the insurance after the first year.
Then someone would have had an accident with this bike.
He would file a third party claim against the bike owner
and both parties would
meet in court.  The court saw who would
pay the compensation?  The bike is not even insured.
Then the court decided that if any two-
wheeler or bike is purchased, then it
is mandatory to have 5 years of third party coverage and comprehensive coverage for the first one year.  That
means, in the first year, your bike will also be
covered under this insurance and there will be third party
coverage also.  The third party premium for the next 4 years is
taken in advance from you at the time of purchasing the new bike so that
if anyone else gets harmed by this bike,
it can at least be compensated by this insurance policy.
After completion of one year,
if you want coverage for your bike for the next 4 years, if
you want to cover the damage caused to the bike, then
every year you will have to
renew the Own Damaged Policy, which is
also called OD Policy.  If you do not get this done then you will
not get any coverage for your bike.  The front cover
is also covered for the next four years.  This
policy is called OnePlus 5 Year
Bundled Policy because there is one year of
comprehensive coverage and the next four years
of third party coverage is inbuilt.  Now
till now it has been mentioned that how many types of policies are there.
Now let's talk about what
coverage you get in a first party comprehensive policy.  What is the
biggest damage that can happen to a bike or two wheeler
?  Brother, either
that bike may get stolen or such a big
accident may happen that now this bike
cannot be repaired.  So in such cases, the
claim for the IDV written in the insurance
is received.  The full form of IDV is
Insured Declared Value.  This IDV is the
maximum liability of the insurance company in case of any loss.
Now can we deposit any amount of IDV
?  It's not like that.  For this, IRDA has
set a fixed formula.  Let us
understand it.  Suppose I bought a new bike today
whose ex-showroom price is ₹1 lakh.   As soon as I
buy a new bike,
my IDV will be deducted by 5% from ₹1 lakh under the first insurance.  That means it comes to
₹95,000.  ₹95,000.  One year is completed.  When
my bike gets its first renewal,
15% amount will be deducted from the ex-showroom price.
This year the value of my bike will be ₹85,000.
This depreciation will be 20% on renewal next year.  That
means the
value will be fixed at ₹80,000.  There will be 30% depreciation next year,
40% next year and 50% on the fifth renewal.  That
means the
value of a bike worth ₹1 lakh now becomes ₹00 in insurance.  There
is no such slab or any depreciation chart after 5 years.  Any insurance company
can value your bike higher or lower.
This is a matter between the insurance company and the insured.
So, whichever company offers you more
value, you
can take the policy of that company after five years.
But this ideal slab will have to be followed for 5 years.
Now many people will also think that
who checks online?  I
put more value on it.  So the company will take the money.
No one throws a tantrum while taking money.
But when the claim comes, they will follow these guidelines of IRDA
and the IDV claim will be given as per the
age and depreciation slab of your bike or two wheeler.
Now it is not necessary that the bike gets stolen directly
or there is a major accident.   There are some
minor accidents in between in
which we have to get the bike repaired,
so how much claim do we get?
For this, the edge of the bike or two wheeler is seen.
Depending on the age of the bike, depreciation is charged on the replacement of parts, i.e.,
on the parts that are replaced, that is, the
part has become that
old along with the bike.  If we provide a new part, you will
not get the full claim for it.   There
is a slab of depreciation.  But if you
want that
such deduction should not be made from your claim amount on replacement of parts, then
for this you can also take add-on of zero depreciation.  By
doing this, whether your bike is
3 years old or 4 years old,
depreciation on its parts will not be
deducted.  Full MRP claim will be available.
But you get this zero depreciation add-on
only for the first four years.  Some
companies offer it even after 5 years.
But then it becomes expensive because the
liability of the insurance company keeps increasing with the age of the bike.
Now, we should include
add-ons like zero depreciation
in our policy with almost every bike or two-wheeler.
But now I am going to tell you about such an
add-on which those who buy expensive bikes should
definitely take.  And its name
is Return to Invoice RTI or Invoice
Cover.  Suppose there is a very expensive bike worth ₹5
lakh, ₹6 lakh, ₹8 lakh and that bike gets
stolen after 2 years.  Now
how much claim will the insurance company give as per the IDV mentioned.
But that IDV will not buy a new bike today
because the ex-showroom
price is also different and apart from that I had
also paid the insurance money and the RC
also cost a lot.  So the session for this
is RTI add on.  If your bike is totaled or stolen after taking this add-on,
you do not get the claim of just the IDV.
You get the on-road price at the time you purchased the bike.  In which,
apart from the ex-showroom price of the bike, the
insurance money paid by you and apart from that the
registration charges are also added
together and the on-road price claim
is given.  Now through this RTI add on
we can cover the risk of the gap between the on road price of the new bike and its current
IDV.
Companies provide RTI only for the first three-four years.  So if your
bike is very expensive then you should definitely take this add on.
Apart from this, if there is heavy rainfall in your city
, water logging occurs
, water accumulates, and the
bike or two-wheeler has to be taken through that water, then
you can also take an add-on of engine protection, in
which if water enters the engine
and any damage occurs due to it, then
this insurance policy will cover that too.  Now
friends, finally comes the most important add on.
This is personal accidental cover for owner [ __ ]
driver.  That means, if the registered owner of this bike,
whose name is in the RC,
rides this bike, then he can also have
a personal accidental insurance for the whole year.
If
he dies in an accident while riding this bike or becomes
disabled, or loses any
part of his body like hands, legs, eyes, then a
claim can be taken under this cover.   The
maximum coverage amount is ₹15 lakh, which
is available only on death and permanent total disability.  Apart from this, minor disabilities are
also covered in it.  Now all my
dear viewers who are watching this video
and their two wheeler is registered in their name,
please add this personal
accidental policy to your insurance.  It doesn't
cost much.
Coverage is available for ₹350 to ₹400 for one year.  And you already know
how risky it is to travel on your bike or two wheeler on Indian roads and Indian traffic.  Till now I have
told you three-four optional covers.  These
are optional covers i.e. add ons.  That means
you do not get this coverage in the standard first party comprehensive policy.
You have to choose this intentionally.
So whatever add-on you need, get it
added to your policy.  Now
friends, let us talk about which two wheeler insurance policy we should buy for ourselves – a first party
comprehensive policy with add-ons or
a third party insurance policy.
So it has a very
simple formula.  If you
want your two wheeler insurance
policy to cover all the damages caused to this bike or two wheeler,
then you should take a first
party comprehensive policy.
You can also add to the policy whatever add-ons I have mentioned according to age and risk.
But if
your bike is very old, is driven very little
and if it meets with an accident, then
you should not make any claim on your bike
because either its condition is already not that good
or you are not interested in making a claim on your bike, then
you should get a third party
insurance policy.  By doing this,
your legal liability i.e. your bike or
two wheeler challan will not be borne and
apart from this, if any third party claim is filed
against us, then this third
party policy will also bear it.  But
please follow my advice that when you buy a new bike,
after the first year,
you must renew the own damage policy for the next four years
because at that time the value of the bike is very
high and hence the risk is also high.
At least during that time period you should keep your bike
covered also.  Now finally friends, the
question arises that we will decide about the insurance policy also.
We have also seen the coverage.  I have
also understood what happens.  But
where can I buy this policy now?  Every day we
see ads online.  You get repeated calls from Policybay, Paytm,
agents or even bike showrooms
to get your policy renewed.
So what is the best option?  Let us
understand this.  See, the premium of third party bike
insurance is
fixed according to the engine CC of your bike.
Suppose your bike
falls in the slab between 75 to 150 cc, then a
fixed premium will be charged from you.  You
buy the policy from anywhere, from any company.   There will be
no variation in price, there will be
no difference.  So it does not matter
where you buy this insurance.  Just keep one thing in
mind while purchasing the policy.
Because
if you buy this policy online without any expert assistance, then the
details of your bike should be
entered correctly.  Be careful
not to issue a policy with wrong details.  If
you are
not very comfortable using mobile apps then you should
buy this policy from an agent or showroom only.  And if
you want to buy a first party comprehensive
policy then you should either
buy this policy from the dealer or showroom or
you should buy it from a trusted agent.
If you buy this first party
comprehensive policy from the showroom, you
get a unique benefit.  If you ever get this
bike repaired after an accident,
you get the facility of cashless repair.  This
means that you will not have to pay advance money to the dealer for that repair.  The
insurance company and the dealer settle this claim directly.
If there is some difference
amount in between then only you have to pay that.
But sometimes you can also get cheaper premium from the agent.
That means if the policy
is available for a very low price and the chances of claim are
less, then you will prefer to go with an agent
and along with this,
you also get personal support from the agent.  You
get one on one attention.  You
can take any advice from him.  So
you will not get that in the case of showroom or dealer.  So
you have to decide whether you want price and support
or cashless repair facility.
Now you tell me,
if someone makes a mistake even after giving so many details, then
who will suffer the loss, you?  So, do share this information
with your friends and family
so that they do not make any
mistake in buying a two-wheeler policy.  Today I have
given you all the information about the coverage of a two wheeler insurance, types of add ons policy and from where you should get this policy.
Next time you go to renew your bike insurance,
you might know a few things better than your agent.
If you like the video then
subscribe to the channel and if you
want to understand and learn insurance deeply then
this is the best place.  Now
you have learned how to take bike insurance
but how to make a claim in this insurance policy
?  What is its step by step
process?  For that
I have made a separate dedicated video for you.  Do
n't miss this.  I am Harvinder Singh, see
you in the next video.  Till
then take care, stay fit and stay healthy.
Jai Hind.